All you have to do is dream.
Dreamgirls is a drama, music film directed by Bill Condon.
A trio of female soul singers cross over to the pop charts in the early
1960s, facing their own personal struggles along the way.
Curtis Taylor Jr., played by Jamie Foxx.
Deena Jones, played by Beyoncé.
James "Thunder" Early, played by Eddie Murphy.
Marty Madison, played by Danny Glover.
Effie White, played by Jennifer Hudson.
Lorrell Robinson, played by Anika Noni Rose.
Dreamgirls  is a 2006 American musical drama film written and directed by Bill Condon and
jointly produced and released by DreamWorks Pictures and Paramount Pictures.
Adapted from the 1981 Broadway musical of the same name, Dreamgirls is a film à clef, a work of fiction taking
strong inspiration from the history of the Motown record label and its superstar act the Supremes.
The story follows the history and evolution of American R&B music during the 1960s and 1970s through the
eyes of a Detroit girl group known as "The Dreams" and their manipulative record executive.
The film adaptation features an ensemble cast, starring Jamie Foxx, Jennifer Hudson, Eddie Murphy and
Beyoncé Knowles with Danny Glover, Anika Noni Rose and Keith Robinson in supporting roles.
In addition to the original compositions by composer Henry Krieger and lyricist Tom Eyen, four
new songs, composed by Krieger with various lyricists, were added for the film.
The film marks the acting debut of Hudson, a former American Idol contestant.
Dreamgirls debuted in four special road show engagements starting on December
4, 2006, before its nationwide release on December 15, 2006.
With a production budget of $80 million, Dreamgirls is one of the most expensive films to
feature a predominant African-American starring cast in American film history.
The film received positive reviews from critics, who particularly praised Condon's direction, the soundtrack, costume and
production design, and performances of the cast, in particular Hudson and Murphy, and grossed $155.4 million worldwide.
At the 79th Academy Awards, the film received a leading eight nominations,
winning Best Supporting Actress (for Hudson), and Best Sound Mixing.
At the 64th Golden Globe Awards, it won three awards, including
for the Best Motion Picture – Musical or Comedy.
The film explores themes of show business, drug addiction,
musical, deceived wife, recording contract.
The tone is emotional.